John Thomas Harrington papers, Inclusive: 1884-1947, undated, Bulk: 1884-1923, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
John Thomas Harrington papers
Inclusive: 1884-1947, undated, Bulk: 1884-1923, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
728
Harrington, John Thomas
4 document boxes and 1 oversized box.
The John Thomas Harrington papers consists of correspondence, financial papers, medical practice materials, and other literary documents from Harrington’s life in Waco, Texas.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Dr. John Thomas Harrington, Jr. was born in 1858 in Chicksaw County, Mississippi, to John Thomas and Margaret Williams Belk Harrington. He attended the Louisville Medical College, the Medical School of St. Louis, and the New York Polyclinic Medical College before establishing his first medical practice back in Mississippi. He then moved to Texas where he lived in Bremond, Sweetwater, El Paso, and Abilene before settling down in Waco in the late 1880s. Here, Harrington was on staff at the Hillcrest and Providence Hospitals, as well as serving as the city physician.
Among his achievements, he was the president of the board of health at El Paso as well as the director of the Epileptic Colony at Abilene for four years. He was a founder of Simmons College (later Hardin Simmons University) at Abilene where he served as secretary-treasurer of the Board of Trustees. Likewise, he helped to organize the McLennan County Medical Society in 1903. Harrington was a member of the Board of Trustees at Baylor University, serving as chairman from 1932 to 1947, and was a co-founder of Baylor Medical College. Additionally, he served as president of the Chemical Oil Company and secretary-treasurer of the Etla Gold Mining Company of Waco.
Dr. Harrington married Genoa Cole at Independence, Texas, in 1884. They had two daughters, Genoa and Jessie, both of whom attended Baylor University and later married. He died in Waco on April 29, 1947.
Scope and Content
The John Thomas Harrington papers include personal correspondence, financial documents, medical practice materials, and family documents. The majority of the material is related to Harrington's medical career and there are no documents associated with his positions in either the Chemical Oil Company or the Etla Gold Mining Company. Also included are a collection of photographs, both identified and unidentified, and artwork.
Arrangement
The John Thomas Harrington papers were organized by material type. The prior organization was primarily kept, including folder titles. The collection is arranged in 5 series: I. Personal Materials, II. Family Documents, III. Literary Productions, IV. Photographs, and V. Oversized Materials: Artwork.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 728. Acquired 1974-06-19
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. “Dr John Thomas Harrington, Jr.” Memorial #9924279. Databases. Accessed 2014 March 2.
Family Search. “John T Harrington, ‘United States Census, 1930.’” The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Geneology Website. Accessed 2014 March 2.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University. College of Medicine -- History.; McLennan County Medical Society (Tex.); White Rock Dairy Farm.
Subjects
Physicians -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Photographs.
- Personal Materials, 1873-1947; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series includes a variety of personal correspondence. Much of the material relates to John Thomas Harrington’s medical career.
  - Correspondence, 1884-1947; 1
    - General, 1894-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Personal (1 of 2), 1884-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Personal (2 of 2), circa. 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Invitations, circa. 1931-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Financial Documents, 1901-1947; 2
    - Banking Records, 1929-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Statements and Receipts (1 of 2), circa. 1919-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Statements and Receipts (2 of 2), circa. 1901-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dairy Farm Ledger, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Medical Practice Material, 1904-1947, undated; 3
    - General, circa. 1904-1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Prescription Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Notes and Articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Literary Productions, 1873-1947; 4
    - Diplomas, 1873, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Notebooks, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Vassar College Catalogue, 1895-1896 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Programs, circa. 1901-1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Certificates, License, Memberships, circa. 1905-1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Medical Advertisements, circa. 1914-1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - John Hopkins- Report of the President, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - John Hopkins University Catalogue, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Farming Advertisements, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - General Advertisements, circa. 1928-1947 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - The Light that Grows by Dawson, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Family Documents, 1895-1933; 2
  This series includes correspondence, notebooks, and journals from Harrington’s family members, including his nephew, Milton M. Miller, and his brother, Henry Harrington.
  - Genoa Cole Harrington, 1894-1933, undated; 1
    - Correspondence, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Literary Productions, circa. 1894-1904 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Journal, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - The Cost of Living by Richards, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Notebook, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Genoa Harrington, undated; 2
    - Notebooks (1 of 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Notebooks (2 of 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jessie Tom Harrington, 1902-1904, undated; 3
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Notebooks (1 of 2), circa. 1902-1904 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Notebooks (2 of 2), circa. 1902-1904 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Milton M. Miller, undated; 4
    - Notebooks (1 of 3), undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Notebooks (2 of 3), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Notebooks (3 of 3), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Henry Harrington, 1932; 5
    - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General, undated; 6
    - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Literary Productions, undated; 3
  This series includes general collected material.
  - Collected Materials, undated; 1
    - Recipes, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Addresses, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - News Paper Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Photographs, undated; 4
  This series includes both identified and unidentified photographs.
  - Identified, undated; 1
    - General, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified, undated; 2
    - General (1 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - General (2 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Oversized, undated (Box 5 OVZ, Folder 1)
- Oversized Materials: Artwork, undated; 5
  This series includes four types of artwork, a charcoal by Genoa Harrington, a matted print of a watercolor, and a hand-colored print.
  - Charcoal by Genoa Cole, Matted Print of Watercolor, Hand-Colored Print (Box 5 OVZ, Folder 1)